<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>treacherous.tech</title>
    <link href="https://treacherous.tech/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://treacherous.tech" />
    <updated>1970-01-01T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Yours Truly</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://treacherous.tech</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Onionshare secure contact form is back online</title>
        <author>
            <name>Yours Truly</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://treacherous.tech/onionshare-back.html"/>
        <id>https://treacherous.tech/onionshare-back.html</id>

        <updated>2022-04-06T00:18:21+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://treacherous.tech/media/posts/20/women-telephone-operators-at-work-12-jpg.jpeg" alt="telephone operator from the olden days" />
                    The Onionshare site went offline for a little while due to some local internet issues where the box is, but it's back on now: That's just one of the hazards of self hosting on my own little DIY clouds.
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://treacherous.tech/media/posts/20/women-telephone-operators-at-work-12-jpg.jpeg" alt="telephone operator from the olden days" />
                <p>The Onionshare site went offline for a little while due to some local internet issues where the box is, but it's back on now: That's just one of the hazards of self hosting on my own little DIY clouds. <a href="https://onionshare.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Onionshare</a> is a secure contact form developed by digital security technologist Micah Lee. I blogged a while back about <a href="https://treacherous.tech/hosting-a-secure-contact-form.html">how to set up a persistent version with a Raspberry Pi</a>.</p>
<p>My point for having it is to essentially offer a reasonably secure online form for users to contact me or send stuff. I've gone this route as most other self-hosted forms are a mess and commercial third-party tools aren't that privacy respecting. For this one to work you need to use the <a href="https://www.torproject.org/download/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Tor Browser</a>.</p>
<p><strong>Throw things at:</strong></p>
<p class="msg--warning"><code><a href="http://entyms3fdn4fyl6lizog6hoztvaqkvv2njmcovslkm55xhahs7nnmiqd.onion/">http://entyms3fdn4fyl6lizog6hoztvaqkvv2njmcovslkm55xhahs7nnmiqd.onion/</a></code></p>
<p>If you're an independent journalist it's also a tool you can use for your sources without too much hassle, but some operational security is advisable as you're essentially asking strangers to send you files that may do anything. This is why I tend to prefer it to be on it's own little device, accessed by a throw-away machine in the middle for file inspection.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Some more notes on the Spotify kerfuffle</title>
        <author>
            <name>Yours Truly</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://treacherous.tech/some-more-notes-on-the-spotify-kerfuffle.html"/>
        <id>https://treacherous.tech/some-more-notes-on-the-spotify-kerfuffle.html</id>

        <updated>2022-04-06T00:18:21+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://treacherous.tech/media/posts/19/spotify-logo-zoom-s.jpg" alt="Cassette tapes that ran Apple programming back around 1978" />
                    This post is a rambling continuation of another one here. Do you need to read that one first? I have no idea. The Spotify story just keeps on giving. What's neat about it is how many cultural zeitgeists and&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://treacherous.tech/media/posts/19/spotify-logo-zoom-s.jpg" alt="Cassette tapes that ran Apple programming back around 1978" />
                <p>This post is a rambling continuation of <a href="https://treacherous.tech/spotify-kerfuffle.html">another one here</a>. Do you need to read that one first? I have no idea.</p>
<p>The Spotify story just keeps on giving. What's neat about it is how many cultural zeitgeists and trends are mashed in a single event. We've got capitalism vs. social responsibility, science literacy vs ignorance, the cult of celebrity, the belief in consumer choice as a source of political and social activism, platform terms of service being substituted as the law of the land on regulating free speech, data rights, privacy, creator control and fair compensation, copyright, and etc. etc. etc. It's all here. The world will burn to an algorithmically generated playlist.</p>
<p>Since Spotify decided to go with Joe Rogan's podcast over Neil Young's music in Young's ultimatum over the talk show's repeated amplifying of pandemic and vaccine misinformation, <a href="https://mediatraffic.org/2022/01/29/spotify-loses-4-billion-in-market-value-after-neil-young-controversy/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">the platform's market value has lost $4 billion</a>. With its <a href="https://americansongwriter.com/spotify-stock-down-25-as-artists-leave-platform-rumors-of-foo-fighters-departing-swirl/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">stock dropping 25%</a>, Joni Mitchell and other performers announcing or rumoured to be considering pulling off of Spotify, it's an amazing little surge of creators showing what control can look like.</p>
<p>My premium account expired yesterday, and so it goes. Spotify has a good user interface. The algorithm is also fairly decent at pitching tunes I'll likely enjoy. For the WFH years of this pandemic, it really was in the background a lot of the time, as I assume it had been for a lot of people. I don't think it's a coincidence that Spotify's value surged as more people were cut off from the outside world, sort of like how the plague times helped Amazon. And again, no one paid attention to the fact that Joe Rogan had a platform there until Spotify decided it was worth paying him $100 million to quit Apple Music and any other platform. So, all around, the teachable lesson here is that platforms should let creators upload where they want, and instead compete for them via better compensation models instead of high-stake gambling of exclusivity.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center" ><img loading="lazy" src="https://treacherous.tech/media/posts/19/Napster_running_on_an_original_iBook_2001-03-11.png" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://treacherous.tech/media/posts/19/responsive/Napster_running_on_an_original_iBook_2001-03-11-xs.png 300w ,https://treacherous.tech/media/posts/19/responsive/Napster_running_on_an_original_iBook_2001-03-11-sm.png 480w ,https://treacherous.tech/media/posts/19/responsive/Napster_running_on_an_original_iBook_2001-03-11-md.png 768w ,https://treacherous.tech/media/posts/19/responsive/Napster_running_on_an_original_iBook_2001-03-11-lg.png 1024w ,https://treacherous.tech/media/posts/19/responsive/Napster_running_on_an_original_iBook_2001-03-11-xl.png 1360w ,https://treacherous.tech/media/posts/19/responsive/Napster_running_on_an_original_iBook_2001-03-11-2xl.png 1600w"  alt="The official Napster client runs on an original iBook running Mac OS 9. The Search and Transfer Manager windows are visible. Several MP3 downloads are underway over a dialup Internet connection. (Wikimedia)" width="800" height="600">
<figcaption >
<p class="mw-mmv-title-para mw-mmv-ttf-container mw-mmv-title-smaller"><span class="mw-mmv-title">The official Napster client runs on an original iBook running Mac OS 9. The Search and Transfer Manager windows are visible. Several MP3 downloads are underway over a dialup Internet connection. (Source: Wikimedia)</span></p>
<div class="mw-mmv-image-metadata-column mw-mmv-image-metadata-desc-column"> </div>
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>What I also really appreciate from the whole embroglio imbroglio is that people are once again talking about copyright and other forms of file streaming. Napster, Limewire, and a load of other pre-web services allowed for decentralised and ubiquitous file sharing. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metallica_v._Napster,_Inc." target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Metalica</a> may not have liked it <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2007/12/08/50-cent-file-sharing-doesn%e2%80%99t-hurt-artists/?guce_referrer=aHR0cHM6Ly93d3cuZ29vZ2xlLmNvbS8&amp;guce_referrer_sig=AQAAAIc1b995LotsgzT0RScovBEP0mzTxAHXMCQSKKu83k_wTmrEevrqxTkAh8YfsDD3hg5nEEg_RNyvOn5f4QIo8_uoHB1RZJfP_y6ZxToKgo-aaSckQ-VkkROHbVnlBF-RQ2y2CpO3DSsyvV1GO5PChEv6yHajGhNBSU1NcyKch5JI" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">but it was good for others</a> in getting attention and interest in their live gigs. Performers didn't really win in the copyright wars. Listeners certainly didn't. We had all these great running between apps, decentralised, networks of fans, running FTP hosts or being torrent seeders (still around to some extent).</p>
<p>What this isn't really about is free speech, though it works in Spotify's interests to frame it that way. It of course has the legal right to host Rogan and any other podcaster it likes. It doesn't have the right to demand market value, subscribers or people looking at their ads. Free speech protection is not about the right to profits.</p>
<p>Related, but at a lower volume, <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2022/jan/27/anti-vaxxers-making-at-least-25m-a-year-from-publishing-on-substack" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">e-newsletter service Substack came under fire last week</a> over the hight volume of anti-vaccine pundits are using its service to reach and grow their audiences. Apparently, these content creators have earned a combine $2.5 milion a year from their Substack subscribers. Now, who know's how may of these wingnuts there are and how much of that amount each is getting. I imagine there are a few bigger voices taking the most of it and then some fringe of the fringe group getting the rest. But Substack gets a percentage of that whole amount, so it's definitely profiting off of covid-29 disinformation.</p>
<p><a href="https://on.substack.com/p/society-has-a-trust-problem-more?r=1im5e&amp;utm_campaign=post&amp;utm_medium=web" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Substack's says</a> it doesn't do content moderation and respects free speech. It's a different situation to Spotify in one very key way: Substack is not buying these people exclusively for its platform. It's not giving a writer several million dollars to just publish on Substack. These writers have kind of an equal footing as any other content creator on Substack. I actually don't think Substack should "censor" content creators either, and <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2020/07/15/substack-launches-defender-a-program-offering-legal-support-to-independent-writers/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Substack does seem to put some money</a> behind it's free speech mantra.</p>
<p>Still, in its own blog post defending its policy, there are a <span style="color: var(--text-editor-body-color); font-family: var(--font-base); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">lot of concepts muddled together, essentially to protect a a business model. Substack is a vanity press. That's fine. The internet runs on them. It's not countering society's "trust problem" with the media. The trust problem is not a free speech problem, it's a media literacy problem. In many ways, Substack works against solving the trust problem, it provides a platform for people to bypass the public scrutiny that builds credibility. At the end of the day, it's an e-newsletter tool. It's hip MailChimp. You know that line "politics is show business for ugly people," right? Exchange "politics" with Substack and "show business" with Onlyfans. That's Substack. <a href="https://www.isdglobal.org/digital_dispatches/anti-vaxxers-qanon-influencers-and-white-nationalists-flocking-to-substack/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">This is why</a> it gets the anti-vaxxes, the QAnons, and the White Nationalists. Not sure how that builds trust. </span></p>
<p>At the center of all of this is the commodity of providing a platform or infrastructure that allows others to express themselves. This then becomes a set of business decisions, mundane, boring and based on bottom lines. Substack, Spotify, Facebook, or whatever other commercial platforms you want to include here are not advocacy organisations. They exist to monetise human behaviours. There are things people want to do on the web, and they exist to facilitate that to turn a profit, through subscriptions, ads, monetising user data or whatever else can be thought of. So long as the free speech protection debate is muddled with profit motives of content platforms, it will be defined as whatever happens to be in the best interest of business, which can always change. Platform terms of service are a horrible substitute for good laws and protection of rights.</p>
<div class="css-1dbjc4n">
<div id="id__znxag5kkn" class="css-1dbjc4n" aria-labelledby="id__78yjugh30ik id__9e7153902bm">
<div class="css-1dbjc4n r-1s2bzr4">
<div id="id__9e7153902bm" class="css-1dbjc4n r-1ets6dv r-1867qdf r-1phboty r-rs99b7 r-1ny4l3l r-1udh08x r-o7ynqc r-6416eg" aria-labelledby="id__ocpzqgcu5bg id__les79acjiqo" data-testid="card.wrapper">
<div id="id__ocpzqgcu5bg" class="css-1dbjc4n r-140t1nj r-pm2fo r-zmljjp r-rull8r r-qklmqi r-1adg3ll" aria-hidden="true" data-testid="card.layoutLarge.media">
<div class="css-1dbjc4n r-1adg3ll r-1udh08x"> </div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Some notes on the Spotify kerfuffle</title>
        <author>
            <name>Yours Truly</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://treacherous.tech/spotify-kerfuffle.html"/>
        <id>https://treacherous.tech/spotify-kerfuffle.html</id>

        <updated>2022-04-06T00:18:21+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://treacherous.tech/media/posts/18/Time-coded_vinyl_record.jpg" alt="" />
                    Here it is Friday after work, and I am without an obligatory Spotify playlist filling the background while settling into the dubious plan of attempting to write something on the blog. Why? because I canceled my Spotify family plan&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://treacherous.tech/media/posts/18/Time-coded_vinyl_record.jpg" alt="" />
                <p>Here it is Friday after work, and I am without an obligatory Spotify playlist filling the background while settling into the dubious plan of attempting to write something on the blog.  Why? because I canceled my Spotify family plan and logged out of the account, and when time allows I'll export my mess of playlists elsewhere and delete it. Why? Because Neil Young (whose music I do enjoy but admittedly rarely listen to) has pulled his work from the platform. Why? Because Spotify paid $100 million to exclusively host a sketchy podcast series hosted by this guy Joe Rogan, who regularly puts out dodgy information about our current pandemic. I also don't really listen to Joe Rogan, and the scant bits and pieces I've heard of his show reaffirm that lifestyle choice. It's a dumpster fire of nonsense. So considering that the current drama is between two people I don't spend much time on, why would I close an account based on it? Let me explain, gentle reader, while listening to Reykjavík's own <a href="http://radio.garden/listen/apparatidj/3Kv37fX2" title="Can someone explain why this site has no https?" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Apparatið radio</a> on <a href="http://radio.garden" title="I enjoy this site, but if you switch to another browser tab it quits." target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">radio.garden</a>.</p>
<p>As is this blog's policy, we're not going to go through the whole background of this story. It's all over the media, so go find it. <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2022/1/25/22900437/neil-young-spotify-joe-rogan-vaccine-misinformation" title="Go on, get the facts before my self indulgent ruminations. I'll wait. I got all night. " target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Find it here</a>. So you might think this story is about dangers of misinformation (disinformation if you think there's strategic intent to deceive), and there's surely elements of that here. Thousands of people are continuing to dro Spotify as I write this and maybe even as you read it (depending on when you're doing that)  for choosing misinformation grifter Joe Rogan over a principled rock icon Neil Young. They are proudly tweeting, facebooking or redditing that they'd jumped over to Apple Music, TIDAL, Bandcamp, and and so on because Spotify is platforming a dangerous anti-vaccine conspiracy nutter.</p>
<p>If that's the case, they're all in for a shock. Rogan left Apple Music not because he got booted out. Spotify just spent heaps of moola for exclusive rights to his show, that's all. Apple was fine with him being there and there's plenty of other legacy Rogan stuff still on its platform. And if you're worried about nutters having a right wing nutters and fascists having a voice, Apple hosts <a href="https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/bannons-war-room/id1485351658" title="Steve Bannon is far worse than Joe Rogan. Rogan is just a narcissist. Bannon has a vision." target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Steve Bannon</a>'s show. I don't know if you can find antisemitic, anti-science podcast TruNews on Apple Music, <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/trunews/id880594743" title="Far more insane than Joe Rogan can hope to be." target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">but you can find it on its iPhone app store</a>. The point: <span style="color: var(--text-editor-body-color); font-family: var(--font-base); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">A bit of searching and you'll find something sketchy on any of the platforms.</span></p>
<p>I don't think Rogan needs to be "deplatformed" or "canceled" or whatever the boomers are alleging the kids call it these days. The government isn't — and certainly shouldn't — censor him. I know some people do think he should be. I think they're wrong, and anyway, it's not going to happen. That word gets thrown around a lot, but censorship is not people deciding to go somewhere else when you're talking. That's just them telling you you're not worth their time. Censorship requires a structure aimed at silencing particular points of view. If you don't get paid for your views, that's not censorship. I've got this whole blog no one's paying for. Millions of people do. Censorship also requires power asymmetry (power, money, access to control regulation, etc.) I can't google any results of weaker parties successfully censoring more powerful or dominant groups. Celebrities aren't censored by audiences who have grown tired of them.</p>
<p>What people are attempting is a boycott, which is actually just more free speech. Neil Young wanted Spotify to choose between his music and Rogan's podcasts after <a href="https://spotifyopenletter.wordpress.com/2022/01/10/an-open-letter-to-spotify/">an open letter</a> to Spotify, signed by hundreds of doctors, asked the platform to implement a misinformation policy following Rogan's show featured a guest promoting various anti-vaccine conspiracies. It's not the only time that's happened. Spotify, in response, removed Young's music. So that's its misinformation policy.</p>
<p>It's important (central, even) to this story that Spotify bought exclusive rights to Rogan's show, and made this choice. It indicates that Rogan's content is part of Spotify's business model. A $100 million bet that a show that occasionally dabbles paranoid conspiracies that put people off life-saving vaccines is not an accident. This comes after another piece of weird news in which Spotify paid $30 million to royal exiles Harry and Meg for a show <a href="https://www.news.com.au/entertainment/celebrity-life/royals/spotify-steps-in-to-bolster-meghan-and-harrys-multimilliondollar-podcast/news-story/550810c42d28be3d8f486e1433243574" title="I would not make a podcast for half that amount." rel="nofollow">they subsequently never made</a>. And all this spending resurfaced the fact that Spotify <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Criticism_of_Spotify#Allegations_of_unfair_artist_compensation" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">pays most artists horribly</a>, <a href="https://variety.com/2021/digital/news/spotify-comedy-royalties-faceoff-1235135127/">wiped a bunch of content of comedians</a> who complained they hadn't been paid, and essentially just being a shitty business <a href="https://www.barrons.com/articles/spotify-has-finally-found-a-profitable-tune-51635346820" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">that's only managed to show a profit in September</a> due to its ad revenues.</p>
<p>So, considering the investment in douche podcasters, treating the majority of content creators horribly, I decided I didn't need to pay into that. And since I was only paying to not hear the ads, I've got no use case for Spotify. <strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">So importantly, boycotters: It's not enough to stop your subscriptions. If you want things to hit Spotify's wallet you need to close your account.</span> </strong>Spotify avoided being in the red by the skin of its teeth and it was due to ads, not your subscriptions, and that's based on accounts and their activity. That's not censorship. Consider all the things you didn't listen to today. All those radio shows you missed, all those dramas you didn't watch because you didn't have the time or they looked stupid. You didn't censor any of them.</p>
<p>That's the good news. Now here's the bad news: The streaming industry sucks. Aside from <a href="https://bandcamp.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Bandcamp</a>, which is limited, there are no real good actors out there. So, you're still going to find on lots of them the horrible payment schemes, the bad podcasters and the ravenous, destructive, snake-eating-its-tale capitalism. That's because the music industry is itself awful, a subset of the exploitative entertainment industry. You can decide to boycott it all, but that may get kind of a grim, and it just means the people who may not be getting paid their worth are making even less.</p>
<p>So choose, but as DJ Gandalf says, choose wisely. Maybe pick a service that's not spending millions of dollars for exclusive rights to elevate hateful trolls and flat-earthers. Just remember that their existence is a whack-a-mole problem that spans all platforms of any decent size, and the mitigation needed is in education and better access to good information, and the sorts of social investment that don't create nihilistic hordes braying for an apocalypse that would be preferable to their wretched, vacuous existence and so are prime to believe anyone willing to tell them that sweet, sweet doom is finally happening. Carpet baggers are nothing new, and they've always known how to make a buck. The best you can hope for is a platform not going out of its way to turn them into multi-millionaires.</p>
<p>And now here's more bad news: We gave our freedom away, or let it be dragged away. And I'm talking about file formats, interpretability, the right to copy your own media and use it anywhere you want. While everyone's chirping their happiness of switching to Apple Music, the voice in the back of my head still holds Apple more than a little responsible for this mess. When it went down the DRM route in iTunes, it was a step towards the streaming world. Along the way we lost mixtapes and burned CDs or MP3s that could be moved from this to that device regardless of who made it or what software it's running.</p>
<p>The first format I bought with my own money was vinyl. I think I was in the 5th grade give or take a year, I had a couple of dollars at a garage sale up the road from home and picked up Janis Joplin's "Cheap Thrills." Had no idea what was going in in that, just taken by the Robert Crumb cover art., but obviously someone bought the album, and now was being resold. My sister and I still debate who's album that one actually belonged to, but it was mine. The thing about records is that they're not terribly portable.</p>
<p>File format evolution has been about shrinking things and making them portable. Vinyl was good for visual artists, and as formats got smaller they lost out, until most people were just looking at thumbnail images. During that transition, there was a brief, sweet spot for music fans between cassette tapes and burnable CDs, and then the early file sharing. But then the more copiable and digitised and intangible music became, more musicians started losing out. There's a whole history in this period on battles over intellectual property, copyright reform, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pirate_Party" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">even a political movement I was keen on for a while</a>. Some good ideas started fermenting around that time and still exist, such as <a href="https://creativecommons.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Creative Commons</a>. But it taught the music industry new tricks. Criminalise uncontrolled file sharing and lower the cost barriers of file access, and also don't really still give that much cash back to content creators. Shrinking things has profit. Portability, not so much. Now the industry isn't even about purchasing the music files, just accessing them in lease contracts on specific apps in which whenever you complete a track some lucky performer somewhere you'll never pay to see live because of a pandemic will get $0.0033. Meanwhile, profits the platform suck in from your $10 per month will help it throw bags of cash at of some fuckwit you never listen to whose only skill is preying on the simple minded and the angry.</p>
<p>So, I'll probably make another Faustian bargain on some other service. You won't hear which one it is until I quit that one too, though. I'll give one free advertising when there's a good creator controlled service.</p>
<p><strong>&gt; Find more random thoughts on all this <a href="https://treacherous.tech/some-more-notes-on-the-spotify-kerfuffle.html">here</a>.</strong></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Encryption is not a crime, it&#x27;s a deterrence</title>
        <author>
            <name>Yours Truly</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://treacherous.tech/encryption-is-not-a-crime-its-a-deterrence.html"/>
        <id>https://treacherous.tech/encryption-is-not-a-crime-its-a-deterrence.html</id>
            <category term="encryption"/>

        <updated>2022-04-06T00:18:21+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://treacherous.tech/media/posts/17/keys-261412860438709cZV.jpg" alt="" />
                    In which, for reasons unknown, the British government tries once again to make a villain out of a technological function that makes everyone safer online. Tl;dr: Lots of things break and nothing in the stated goal is achieved. UPDATE&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://treacherous.tech/media/posts/17/keys-261412860438709cZV.jpg" alt="" />
                <p class="msg msg--highlight  msg--warning"><strong>In which, for reasons unknown, the British government tries once again to make a villain out of a technological function that makes everyone safer online.</strong></p>
<p><strong>Tl;dr: Lots of things break and nothing in the stated goal is achieved.</strong></p>
<hr>
<p><strong>UPDATE (21/01/2022):</strong> UK data watchdog, The Information Commissioner’s Office, agrees with me <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2022/jan/21/end-to-end-encryption-protects-children-says-uk-information-watchdog" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">that properly implemented end-to-end encryption keeps kids safer online</a>.</p>
<hr>
<p>The UK Home Office <a href="https://www.wired.co.uk/article/uk-encryption-facebook-home-office-nspcc" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">is back on its anti-encryption campaign</a>. This time it's with an costly and fairly lewd (more on that shortly) public relations blitz aimed at reframing an important but usually invisible security configuration as something akin to a pervy booth at the back of a nude dancing club instead of, say, the function that keeps your banking details, medical records, important business and personal communications confined to just those you think should see them.</p>
<p>In this instalment of the Very British Crypto Wars, Priti Patel's team has signed a £534,000 contract with advertising firm M&amp;C Saatchi to reframe backdooring your security away from being a privacy or security concern to make it "about the children" and the notion that encryption is keeping police from tackling child exploitation online. This is also <a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-57050689" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">not the first time to use fly that flag</a>. The Home Office is also working with longtime alley in this battle, the still very misguided NSPCC, which still campaigns that children will be safer only if their communications are some how easer to exploit by adults unknown.</p>
<p>This is a marketing campaign aimed at turning public opinion on a topic that there's very little knowledge about. Wouldn't be the first time. Aside from a blitzkrieg of propaganda in various tabloids and a “partnership” with The Sun to really ramp things up with Conservatives favourite demographic, and one weird, slightly creepy PR stunt.</p>
<p>According to<a href="https://www.independent.co.uk/tech/government-encryption-whatsapp-phone-security-b1994758.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"> leaked documents on all this</a>, M&amp;C Saatchi notes that “'most of the public have never heard' of end-to-end encryption, one presentation slide about the campaign states – “people can be easily swayed” on the issue." To that end, they recommend going for the ick factor, getting people to not think about privacy and just go for feeling repulsed in a more fact-free environment. And here's where it gets weird. The stunt will be to place a glass box somewhere in public, a high street or shopping mall or some such place, one supposes. In the glass box, The Home Office, with the blessing of an NSPCC and some other charities aimed around children's issues, will pay a child to be locked in the box with an adult male who will leer sexually at them.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Inside the box, there are two actors; one child and one adult. Both strangers. The child sits playing on their smart phone. At the other end of the box, we see an adult sat on a chair also on their phone, typing away. ... The adult occasionally looks over at the child, knowingly. Intermittently through the day, the ‘privacy glass’ will turn on and the previously transparent glass box will become opaque. Passers by won’t be able to see what’s happening inside. In other words, we create a sense of unease by hiding what the child and adult are doing online when their interaction can’t be seen.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>First, yuck. It sounds like something PETA would do, like when they hire a model to sit naked in a cage in an attempt to make people consider going vegan. Only it's worse, and involves a minor. It also makes you wonder what showbiz parent will think that's a good career move for their tween: Go sit in public somewhere while a strange guy you're confined with ogles at you for the day. For people who try to position themselves as interested in child protection, they have a strange way of showing it.</p>
<p>There are lots of reasons a flailing government might want to detract from all its current scandals by looking for new boo scaries everywhere, and <a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/59964656" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">this campaign isn't doing that well</a>. But let's stick to the main point it's trying to make: child safety. So here it goes: <strong>Encryption keeps children safe.</strong> (note: it's not an age thing, it works the same for everyone). It keeps them safe when transmitting data on whatever network they need to access to use it. Keeps their communications from being profiled by myriad trackers that exist in the surveillance capitalist economy. The Home Office doesn't like <a href="https://www.apple.com/uk/privacy/features/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Apple's implementation</a>. Who else doesn't? Third party data traders. Encrypted services mean when you call or text your child, there's a chance that stays between your family, like when you talk with them at home. Many families use WhatsApp, which does have strong encryption. They should be using <a href="https://signal.org/">Signal</a>: Strong encryption and a lot of other features to make sure your offspring's data isn't where it shouldn't be. Use it for your family while you can still get it in this country.</p>
<p>The Plague Times have led to more than one school lockdown, when we had to suddenly share are WFH lives across the kitchen table with one or more children trying to navigate classes via a series of Zoom or Teams calls with their classes and doing homework via a number of SaaS platforms. A lot of us manage their clubs memberships, school fees, schedules, teacher reports and social  through websites with questionable user interface choices. One thing you want on your device and in those platforms carrying all that data is strong encryption. I'll take a wonky interface if I'm fairly certain my kid's itinerary isn't being captured mid-way through transmission across the series of connections that make up how communication networks work.</p>
<p>Back-dooring encryption, or policy to weaknesses in it won't work for a number of reasons, it would make things worse and require a rabbit's warren of other dystopian policy choises. You'd also need to legislate a national internet and close access to foreign services that won't subject themselves to local laws, and legislate against tools such as VPNs. You'd need to organise a system for storing master-keys and accessing them in ways that won't be compromised by insider threats or foreign governments. And lots and lots of blocking. Like the blocking that should be keeping me from watching the show I'm watching right now because I don't subscribe to that service (hypothetically speaking).</p>
<p>There are other places where governments try to ban privacy and instil this idea of "#NoPlaceToHide". You don't want to live in them. Some people go to great lengths to leave them and get asylum somewhere else. As much as Priti Patel attacks encryption, she likes to have a go at them, too... particularly when they're at sea.</p>
<p>There are a lot of ways to increase protection of children, all of which this government doesn't want to do. Increase spending on social services, access to good information, better education, and all the things for which this Tory government has cut funding. Incorporate targeted content across something like the BBC, whose funding this government is also working on freezing. Fund better investigative policing tools and teams, which this government also doesn't want to do. Tax big corporations, inclusive of the tech giants utilising strong encryption, to fund these and many other things instead of continuing to let them dodge it. Facebook (Meta) will happily fight a government about encryption so long as it doesn't have to face it over taxes.</p>
<p>So, there are a lot of solutions to the stated problem. The point of weakening or creating backdoors to encrypted systems isn't about safety, it's about what it's always been about; it's about control.</p>
<hr>
<h3>More on this</h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://neilzone.co.uk/2022/01/a-prohibition-on-end-to-end-encryption-could-leave-you-with-noplacetohide-and-thats-not-a-good-thing" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">A prohibition on end to end encryption could leave you with #NoPlaceToHide. And that's not a good thing.</a> = a list of ways this policy leads to bad things by Internet, telecoms and tech lawyer Neil Brown</li>
<li><a href="https://alecmuffett.com/article/15742" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Why we need #EndToEndEncryption and why it’s essential for our safety, our children’s safety, and for everyone’s future #noplacetohide</a>. Many good reasons by security engineer Alec Muffett </li>
<li><a href="https://www.openrightsgroup.org/campaign/save-encryption/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Save Encryption</a>. Updates on the situation by Open Rights Group.</li>
</ul>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Happy 2022: Quit more</title>
        <author>
            <name>Yours Truly</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://treacherous.tech/happy-2022-quit-more.html"/>
        <id>https://treacherous.tech/happy-2022-quit-more.html</id>

        <updated>2022-04-06T00:18:21+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://treacherous.tech/media/posts/16/uhffszjrfec51.webp" alt="" />
                    Happy new year. It's a new year and I somehow feel obligated to make a blog post to mark that even though I kind of have writer's block and can't think of anything to write about. Fortunately, this is&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://treacherous.tech/media/posts/16/uhffszjrfec51.webp" alt="" />
                <p class="dropcap">Happy new year. It's a new year and I somehow feel obligated to make a blog post to mark that even though I kind of have writer's block and can't think of anything to write about. Fortunately, this is a blog, and doesn't really have to be about much anything.</p>
<p>It's around this time of year I like to take stock of my online presence and various hard drives and see what to keep, delete, or wipe and repeat. One of the nice things about using a password manager and app-based 2FA is that you can keep a nice running list of all the online accounts you've got. <a href="https://keepassxc.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">KeePassXC</a> tells me how many hundreds of accounts I have floating around. If you want to both strengthen your use of passwords and start and audit of all the places you have an account, set up a password manager, and as you use each account, reset the password to some random 32+ character monster you'll never remember, and keep a record of where you're going online at the same time. The best way to start with a password manager is to just set one up and go. Instead of trying to add all your accounts in one go (if you have a lot of them) just add them as you visit the websites. In about a month, you'll have the majority (if not all) of your important accounts. So there's a new year's PSA for you.</p>
<h3>The website</h3>
<p>I'm temporarily closing some buggy things. Closed the onion mirror of this blog and the onionshare contact form for a bit until I can make these things more stable. Will also be looking for a flat-site generator to replace Publii, which started strong, but the bugs are becoming kind of annoying. It edits kind of wonky. Select text to delete and it deletes the paragraph above. Weird. </p>
<h3>Online accounts</h3>
<p><strong>Delete: </strong>Amongst many things, Slack. A few years ago I went from 0 to 8 Slacks in just a couple of months, and I currently use 1 of them, and not even that frequently. The one I controlled was easy. As an administrator, I just deleted it. But depending on the version of Slack being used, you may or may not be able to simply opt out. To remove myself from some, I need to contact the administrator. On at least one, I'm sure they've gone AWOL. You shouldn't have to talk to anyone to remove yourself from an online service. Slack was supposed to put an end to emails. It just created a deluge of meaningless chatter. No new Slacks. And need to post in existing ones I want out. </p>
<p><strong>Keep:</strong> From the collection of digital collateral to roll on with, I'll stick with Publii, the app I'm using to make this blog. It's still glitchy and unfinished, and I can't yet justify using a premium version of it until they make this one work right, but it's maybe the best open source tool for throwing a simple, flat website on the web. Publii, Github and a reasonable domain management service are all that are running this show. The only thing I'm paying for is the domain.</p>
<p><strong>Wipe and repeat</strong>: I keep some Protonmail addresses, and will even add one to the contact page here soonish. Unless you're also chatting with it using a Protonmail account as well, I don't particularly rate it as greatly enhancing security, and the spam/junk filtering is crap. I do regular wipes of the account though, and some people still want to send an email.</p>
<h3>Socials</h3>
<p>I quite Facebook a couple of years back, and have not really missed it. In fact, it immediately made checking in on the web better. Am still in the metaverse via Insta and WhatsApp, but single-use apps are where its at. Quit more social sites, or understand why you're on them. Actually, here I recommend <a href="https://twitter.com/anildash/status/1477313627598299137" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Anil Dash's resources</a> on how to wipe your social accounts for new years and new starts. I'm just about to check out a Glitch app on how to "KonMari" Twitter followers <a href="https://glitch.com/~tokimeki-unfollow" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">here</a>, and highly recommend the process. I usually do this manually, but am happy to see something that makes the process more interesting.</p>
<h3>2022 digital resolutions</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Quit more.</strong> Close more accounts, and make my web more ephemeral. I tend to be a volatile user, but I create lots of accounts often just to see what the shiny looking thing does. My goal this year is to close more online things than I open. Quitting another one of the big companies is still on my list. I still have some Amazon and Google services running and would be happy to move off.</li>
<li><strong>Blog more.</strong> I wrote maybe 6 things last year (no, I'm not counting). Blog shorter, care less about form and style and be a bit more creative and messy (if you can believe it). </li>
<li><strong>Tech less.</strong> I've downsized my devices in the last couple of years, and could still do some more culling. Like everything else, each thing should be justifying its existence in the horde. </li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>This site is basically always a test site... now here&#x27;s some AI generated images</title>
        <author>
            <name>Yours Truly</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://treacherous.tech/this-site-is-basically-always-a-test-site.html"/>
        <id>https://treacherous.tech/this-site-is-basically-always-a-test-site.html</id>
            <category term="meta"/>

        <updated>2022-04-06T00:18:21+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://treacherous.tech/media/posts/15/The_source_TradingCard.jpg" alt="" />
                    I broke the git workflow again. It's pretty easy to do. So I think I fixed it, and I'm testing it out. Here's some AI generated wombo.art made based on some text I typed into it. Did I make&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://treacherous.tech/media/posts/15/The_source_TradingCard.jpg" alt="" />
                <p>I broke the git workflow again. It's pretty easy to do. So I think I fixed it, and I'm testing it out. Here's some AI generated <a href="https://app.wombo.art/">wombo.art</a> made based on some text I typed into it. Did I make the art, or a machine, or some mechanical turks toiling away somewhere for pennies? Can I turn them into NFTs? What's the creator control in this (not considering ToS for the time being). From where comes the actual source material, and how much is sampled? I sense a big growth in all this and also many, many legal battles.</p>
<div class="gallery-wrapper"><div class="gallery"  data-is-empty="false" data-columns="3">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://treacherous.tech/media/posts/15/gallery/Brexit_TradingCard.jpg" data-size="939x1516"><img loading="lazy" src="https://treacherous.tech/media/posts/15/gallery/Brexit_TradingCard-thumbnail.jpg" alt="Brexit" width="720" height="1162"></a>
<figcaption>Boris Johnson eating gammon in a field of red poppies</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://treacherous.tech/media/posts/15/gallery/eye_cell_TradingCard.jpg" data-size="936x1508"><img loading="lazy" src="https://treacherous.tech/media/posts/15/gallery/eye_cell_TradingCard-thumbnail.jpg" alt="Too many eyes watching in prison" width="720" height="1160"></a>
<figcaption>Eye Cell</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://treacherous.tech/media/posts/15/gallery/source_meeting.jpg" data-size="938x1524"><img loading="lazy" src="https://treacherous.tech/media/posts/15/gallery/source_meeting-thumbnail.jpg" alt="Source Meeting" width="720" height="1170"></a>
<figcaption>A meeting in the rain to exchange documents in autumn</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://treacherous.tech/media/posts/15/gallery/The_hunger.jpg" data-size="939x1507"><img loading="lazy" src="https://treacherous.tech/media/posts/15/gallery/The_hunger-thumbnail.jpg" alt="The hunger" width="720" height="1156"></a>
<figcaption>Carnivorous rabbits in a humid jungle at night</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://treacherous.tech/media/posts/15/gallery/the_pirates_TradingCard.jpg" data-size="941x1520"><img loading="lazy" src="https://treacherous.tech/media/posts/15/gallery/the_pirates_TradingCard-thumbnail.jpg" alt="The Pirates" width="720" height="1163"></a>
<figcaption>Pirates fighting business men at sea</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://treacherous.tech/media/posts/15/gallery/The_source_TradingCard.jpg" data-size="928x1516"><img loading="lazy" src="https://treacherous.tech/media/posts/15/gallery/The_source_TradingCard-thumbnail.jpg" alt="The Source" width="720" height="1176"></a>
<figcaption>A source encrypting files for a journalist</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://treacherous.tech/media/posts/15/gallery/umbrella_TradingCard.jpg" data-size="929x1511"><img loading="lazy" src="https://treacherous.tech/media/posts/15/gallery/umbrella_TradingCard-thumbnail.jpg" alt="Umbrella" width="720" height="1171"></a>
<figcaption>umbrella under a street lamp</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Testing on production (again)</title>
        <author>
            <name>Yours Truly</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://treacherous.tech/test-on-prod.html"/>
        <id>https://treacherous.tech/test-on-prod.html</id>
            <category term="meta"/>

        <updated>2022-04-06T00:18:21+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://treacherous.tech/media/posts/14/doc-frankenstein.jpg" alt="" />
                    November: I did it again. September: I killed my blog the other day. That's not why I haven't been posting so much. I mean, you can look at the date of the last post and realise my lack of&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://treacherous.tech/media/posts/14/doc-frankenstein.jpg" alt="" />
                <p><strong>November:</strong></p>
<p><span style="color: var(--text-editor-body-color); font-family: var(--font-base); font-size: inherit;">I did it again.</span></p>
<p><strong style="color: var(--text-editor-body-color); font-family: var(--font-base); font-size: inherit;">September:</strong></p>
<p>I killed my blog the other day. That's not why I haven't been posting so much. I mean, you can look at the date of the last post and realise my lack of blogging isn't down to technical difficulties.</p>
<p>In other news, someone also unplugged my Raspberry Pi, killing some of my onion services. It was a whole thing, not worth getting into. Anyway, rebuilt it and now just seeing if my local repo is still connecting to my Github Pages via this Publii app so I can go back to ignoring it again for the usual reasons.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Notes on Apple&#x27;s CSAM scanning announcement</title>
        <author>
            <name>Yours Truly</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://treacherous.tech/apple-csam-scan.html"/>
        <id>https://treacherous.tech/apple-csam-scan.html</id>

        <updated>2022-04-06T00:18:21+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://treacherous.tech/media/posts/13/stays-on-your-iphone.jpg" alt="iPhone slogan: What Happens on your iPhone stays on your iPhone." />
                     (Or: "Screeching voices from the minority")&nbsp; Last week (on Thursday, 5 August) Apple announced planned changes to its operating systems and iCloud services that have (re)ignited debates on the limits of security, privacy and safety. In a nutshell:&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://treacherous.tech/media/posts/13/stays-on-your-iphone.jpg" alt="iPhone slogan: What Happens on your iPhone stays on your iPhone." />
                
    <h2 id="or-screeching-voices-from-the-minoritynbsp">
      (Or: "Screeching voices from the minority")&nbsp;
    </h2>

  <p>
    Last week (on Thursday, 5 August) Apple announced planned changes to its operating systems and iCloud services that have (re)ignited debates on the limits of security, privacy and safety. In a nutshell: Apple announced it plans to update all Apple devices with the capability to automatically scan images as they are backed up in iCloud against a database of known child sexual abuse material (CSAM) that is managed by&nbsp;the National Center for Missing &amp; Exploited Children (NCMEC). Apple is also rolling out changes to accounts registered to children, in which iMessage images sent or received will also be scanned (client side, meaning on the device itself, not the server) for sexual material, and Apple would ping the kid's folks when it hits a positive.
  </p>

  <p>
    <strong>Before moving on, here's my pithy take</strong><strong>:</strong> this amounts to a backdoor. It bypasses encryption and both device and account security. It introduces a significant shift in Apple's priorities and previously stated business interests away from a brand based on user-centric privacy and security. Instead, we have what could be seen from a marketing point of view as "family friendly," while also finding ways to end arguments it's been having with various interest groups and U.S. federal agencies. It's dangerous at the user level, will do little to actually thwart the problems it aims to solve and globally, it introduces a dangerous precedence.
  </p>

  <p>
    As a technologist working with media, human rights and anti-corruption groups globally and as a parent with a keen interest in child safety locally, I've got a good amount of skin in this game. I wouldn't want this level of invasion on devices run by either my kid, my work contacts, or myself. That said, The issue of CSAM is absolutely and indisputably a high priority, and while I have seen many well-reasoned and insightful points made from both sides of this debate, I've also come across more than a few really horrible takes. More on that later. First, here's a smattering of the different arguments put forward by people with deeper thinking on the matter than yours truly...
  </p>

    <h3 id="some-links">
      Some links
    </h3>

  <ul>
    <li><strong>Apple -&nbsp;<a href="https://www.apple.com/child-safety/" target="_blank">Expanded Protections for Children</a><br></strong>It makes sense to start here as it's to what everything that will follow is responding. In this, we're not getting into the parts on "Communication safety in Messages" or "Expanding guidance in Siri and Search" which are all, in the end, some reporting tools and safety messaging aimed at minors. The part to&nbsp; look at is on CSAM detection. Skip the marketing text and get down to the "More Information" section. Check out the PDF called "CSAM Detection — Technical Summary" and the three technical summaries to get Apple's implementation of all this.<br><br></li><li><strong>NCMEC - <a href="https://www.missingkids.org/blog/2019/post-update/end-to-end-encryption" target="_blank">End-to-End Encryption: Ignoring Abuse Won't Stop It</a><br></strong>The National Center for Missing &amp; Exploited Children maintains the CSAM database Apple would use. I did not find (in my only couple-minutes search) an official statement on the current issues around its collaboration with Apple, but the above was written in 2019, is still prominently featured from the organisation's homepage, and reflects its general stance on all these issues. As the other main player in this story, its views should be seen and understood. I don't think anyone on either side of the debate has any issue with its central cause, thinks its trivial or not important, or has any interest in defending or protecting abusers.&nbsp; In fact, many people who are knowledgeably criticising Apple's implementation of this database actively work in safety and protection of numerous at-risk groups.<br><br></li><li><strong>Ben Lovejoy in 9to5mac -&nbsp;<a href="https://9to5mac.com/2021/08/05/scanning-for-child-abuse-images/" target="_blank">Opinion: Four problems with Apple’s reported approach to scanning for child abuse images</a><br></strong>I don't know who Ben is really, or follow this site much but here's a post that lays out a clear overview of many of the main concerns with client-side scanning and this sort of backdoor, or side-door, to your supposedly private and encrypted content on your Apple device. I think of many things I've read, this one is very accessible and gives someone with a casual interest a quick glance of the concerns.<br><br></li><li><strong>Various experts - <a href="https://appleprivacyletter.com/" target="_blank">An Open Letter Against Apple's Privacy-Invasive Content Scanning Technology</a><br></strong>Signed by leading experts in fields of security, safety, privacy, cryptography, researchers and legal experts, this one summarises the concerns raised by organisations such as  Electronic Frontier Foundation,&nbsp; Center for Democracy and Technology,&nbsp; Open Privacy Research Society and others.<br><br></li><li><strong>EFF -&nbsp;<a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2021/08/apples-plan-think-different-about-encryption-opens-backdoor-your-private-life" target="_blank">Apple's Plan to "Think Different" About Encryption Opens a Backdoor to Your Private Life</a><br></strong>Though linked to in the above letter, the&nbsp;Electronic Frontier Foundation's arguments against client-side and (this kind of) iCloud content scanning deserves it's own mention. What is good about this one is its international focus, and the wide ranging implications of this being built into technology for people living under more totalitarian/authoritarian regimes. If you can use hashed datasets to scan for one kind of content, you could use them for many kinds. And if you don't want to do that, maybe rule out operating in large markets around the world. Once opened, the door only swings more widely. To be honest, this is the area in which my day job sits, so the one that gets more of my attention. American's can shout about their constitutional rights and suchlike, fine. I'm interested in users who are depending on the technology they can access being engineered as though they should have those rights, too. If that helps those of us in "the West", it's a nice bonus.<br><br></li><li><strong>Alec Muffet - <a href="https://alecmuffett.com/article/14860" target="_blank">So @pwnallthethings decided to try calling out @wcathcart and @WhatsApp as “scanning content” like Apple; here’s why that’s incorrect &amp; misleading</a><br></strong>There's a load of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Whataboutism" target="_blank">whatabouttery</a>&nbsp;already flying around on this topic, and I'm not going to link to or get into all (or even most) of it, but here's a thoughtful example and a reasoned response, both from people who are respected experts on these issues.&nbsp; And you can find a good exchange on Twitter between the two of them, if that's your thing. People have made similar whataboutism cases about Google, Kaspersky, etc. Many of these actually aren't good comparisons for one reason or another, but even if they were, the "other companies are doing it" argument is a pretty bad one. Something about that annoying thing your parents may have asked you regarding all your friends jumping off tall, dangerous things applies here.</li>
  </ul>

    <h3 id="for-what-its-worthnbsp">
      For what it's worth&nbsp;
    </h3>

  <p>
    My take is that Apple is backing off its promises in the thornier area of privacy and user security, and going more towards family, safety and things that give people warm and squishy feelings. It's own supposedly tightly controlled app store <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/technology/2021/06/06/apple-app-store-scams-fraud/" target="_blank">is filthy with scamware</a>.&nbsp;Also, there remains <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/news/2021/jul/18/what-is-pegasus-spyware-and-how-does-it-hack-phones" target="_blank">still unknown exploits in iOS, leveraged by the NSO Group's Pegasus spyware</a>.&nbsp;And if you're a security researcher digging in the wrong way, <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2020/1/3/21047275/apple-corellium-dmca-lawsuit-copyright-research-jailbreak-security-copyright" target="_blank">Apple may just see you in court</a>. In this particular case, in an internal Apple mailing message&nbsp;from&nbsp;NCMEC's executive director of strategic partnerships, critics of allowing constant content monitoring were dismissed as "<a href="https://twitter.com/evacide/status/1423748333001080833/photo/1" target="_blank">screeching voices of the minority</a>." No one who can speak for Apple has objected to this description.
  </p>

  <p>
    <strong>Perpetrators will bypass this:</strong> This turn toward the "nothing to hide; nothing to fear" crowd is chilling. The CSAM database is a list of cryptographic hashes -- "fingerprints" of the original horrendous content. If an image triggers a positive hit, the authorities can be contacted, or someone can be tasked to review content to confirm it's legitimate. And here's where we start going into the complex rabbit warren. If the fingerprints are too precise, the sick bastards who peddle them can easily work around it. They can change the image format, shave off a pixel or two in the width or height, alter the colour or any number of things. In order to work, hashes need to be what's called "fuzzy," or approximate, so something close enough can trigger it.&nbsp;
  </p>

  <p>
    <strong>Legitimate, private content will be viewed by more people, thus more users have lost their privacy, and more content is is at risk of misuse:</strong> The more this fingerprinting is made approximate, the more false alarms go off, so the more people and processes will be needed to review them. So these legal, private images are being seen by more people, and the number of people that have to be trusted to not be bad actors or sloppy at their work or a target for an attack grows.
  </p>

  <p>
    <strong>New methods of attack: </strong>There's also the problem of an easy attack vector. Anyone can send anyone a WhatsApp message and WhatsApp and iMessage (maybe others) media automatically backs up to iCloud. Anyone can send anyone else an image they never asked for that triggers a positive match. This may seem insane, or at least like an "edge case" proposition. I want you to consider people who are not people you know who deal with threats from regimes or corrupt entities you will likely never have to deal with. If I wanted to discredit a political dissident or rival candidate, it's an option. Shut down an anti-corruption case? Dirty up the reputation of a journalist? You betcha.
  </p>

  <p>
    <strong>New use cases:</strong> I'm not being original on this one, but once this exists as infrastructure, it has to have new use cases. It's almost a law of physics. If I were a government that had a large iPhone user base, so large that losing that market would be painful, I might have my own database of media file hashes I'd want scanned. Maybe it's memes making fun of leaders, or documents that I don't want the public sharing or seeing. Maybe if you don't run my database in my country, and follow my laws with technology you obviously have that makes it trivial to do so, it gets harder to sell iPhones, or for your in-country offices to not get raided.
  </p>

    <h3 id="meanwhile">
      Meanwhile...
    </h3>

  <p>
    So, it would be great if Apple worked with the broader security community on these things. It would also be groovy if some who fancied themselves as "purists" would lay off the "Perfection of Panopticon" act and considered the world as it is.
  </p>

  <p>
    Finally, the really unhelpful counter-argument is to do nothing.&nbsp; The "Why don't parents just pay better attention to their children" thing&nbsp; doesn't fly, and guess what? We live in a society. Why don't people do all kinds of things that they should? We wouldn't 3rd and 4th wave pandemic lockdowns, insane climate disasters, or regimes violating treaties on the use of chemical weapons.
  </p>

  <p>
    Part of the reason Apple is doing what it's doing is that there are segments of public and private sectors, and just the public in general, asking for something to be done. Like it or not, something will be done. Eventually something is always done. My argument would be that investment is better placed in existing, under-funded, under-resourced policing and the use of advanced, warranted and targeted surveillance of these networks of abusers, possibly with the use of taxes these companies should be paying... as a start.
  </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Pegasus notes</title>
        <author>
            <name>Yours Truly</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://treacherous.tech/pegasus-notes.html"/>
        <id>https://treacherous.tech/pegasus-notes.html</id>
            <category term="spyware"/>

        <updated>2022-04-06T00:18:21+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://treacherous.tech/media/posts/12/pegasus.jpg" alt="" />
                     Pegasus mobile phone hacking software has been the week's big news again, following a leak of a list of 50,000 mobile phone numbers, alleged to be active or potential targets of some of the 50 nation state clients&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://treacherous.tech/media/posts/12/pegasus.jpg" alt="" />
                
  <p>
    Pegasus mobile phone hacking software has been the week's big news again, following a leak of a list of 50,000 mobile phone numbers, alleged to be active or potential targets of some of the 50 nation state clients of its maker, the Israel based NSO Group. Investigated by the&nbsp;Organized Crime and Corruption Reporting Project (OCCRP), some of the mobiles from the list have indeed been found to be infected with Pegasus spyware, and the consortium of organisations investigating the data, including Washington Post, Amnesty International The Guardian, PBS, Haaretz, etc. have been publishing articles all week since the news dropped. Making the list are a number of journalists, human rights activists, civil society leaders, political figures and even a few heads of state.
  </p>

  <p>
    The following are just some links and notes that maybe others find interesting and which I can put somewhere that's not my messy Twitter feed. More will likely be added here in the coming days and weeks. Watch this space.
  </p>
<hr class="separator separator--dots" />

    <h3 id="some-links">
      Some links
    </h3>

  <ul>
    <li><a href="https://www.occrp.org/en/the-pegasus-project/" target="_blank">OCCRP's 'The Pegasus Project' investigation and archive</a>.</li><li><a href="https://www.theguardian.com/news/series/pegasus-project" target="_blank">The Guardian's collection of Pegasus Project news</a>.</li><li><a href="https://github.com/mvt-project/mvt" target="_blank">The Mobile Verification Toolkit</a>. This was developed by the Amnesty International Security Lab as a forensics tool to look for signs of Pegasus software, and is not intended for those without some technical background.</li><li><a href="https://blog.cryptographyengineering.com/2021/07/20/a-case-against-security-nihilism/" target="_blank">A case against security nihilism</a>, by&nbsp;Matthew Green.&nbsp; Maybe one of the more important links in the list. It's easy to look at all this and think there is no hope. There is hope. <em>They</em> (whoever or whatever "they" is for you) are not all powerful. You are not powerless.&nbsp;</li><li><a href="https://cdn.occrp.org/projects/project-p/#/" target="_blank">Explore the data as OCCRP releases it</a>.</li><li><a href="https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/research/2021/07/forensic-methodology-report-how-to-catch-nso-groups-pegasus/" target="_blank">Forensic Methodology Report: How to catch NSO Group’s Pegasus</a>, by Amnesty International's Security Lab<br></li>
  </ul>
<hr class="separator separator--dots" />

    <h3 id="some-notes-amp-asides">
      Some notes &amp; asides
    </h3>

  <p>
    That NSO Group is an Israeli company is an important fact in the story. Just like it was important that The Internet Research Agency was a Russian troll farm, or Hacking Team was Italian, based in EU. NSO Group is a direct outgrowth of the IDF. The NSO Group's technical support for tyrannical regimes around the globe to target their opponents, critics and observers is directly tied to Israel's continued occupation of Palestine. When people say the occupation is a laboratory, things like Pegasus are the exports. Tested in Gaza and West Bank, deployed by anti-democratic paranoid regimes against their critics.
  </p>

  <p>
    NSO Group <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/thomasbrewster/2016/08/25/everything-we-know-about-nso-group-the-professional-spies-who-hacked-iphones-with-a-single-text/?sh=656e910b3997" target="_blank">has a symbiotic relationship with Israel's Unit 8200</a>, a signals intelligence wing of the IDF. Talent and tools <a href="https://www.haaretz.com/israel-news/tech-news/idf-vs-nso-8200-battle-israel-cyber-talent-getting-dark-1.9929433">flow both ways</a> in this relationship. <a href="https://twitter.com/iblametom/status/1417872410246885388">The company claims</a> that its spyware is only used for "legitimate criminal and anti-terrorism investigations." The company also claims it has no control how its software is used and no access to its client's data, so one thing or the other or both are false.&nbsp;&nbsp;It sells to governments known for obsessive levels of human rights violations. If you sell guns to on-the-record sociopaths and serial killers, you can't claim ignorance in how they'll be used. <br>
  </p>

  <p>
    Knowledge of how the NSO Group's software has been used by regimes to target critics is not new, but the current information about it is more sweeping than ever before. There will be a lot of misinformation and disinformation in the coming days and weeks as countries deny spying, NSO Group denies everything, and hyperbole sometimes takes over instead of fact. Read or watch carefully.
  </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>The machine in the middle</title>
        <author>
            <name>Yours Truly</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://treacherous.tech/tails.html"/>
        <id>https://treacherous.tech/tails.html</id>
            <category term="yolo tech"/>

        <updated>2022-04-06T00:18:21+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://treacherous.tech/media/posts/11/usb.jpg" alt="USB stick closeup" />
                     Create a weigh station to open strange files from the internet. Here's another instalment in our irregular YOLO tech series. If you've been following the news, then you'll be up on the latest about Israeli spyware vendor NSO&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://treacherous.tech/media/posts/11/usb.jpg" alt="USB stick closeup" />
                
    <h3 id="create-a-weigh-station-to-open-strange-files-from-the-internet">
      Create a weigh station to open strange files from the internet.
    </h3>

  <p>
    Here's another instalment in our irregular <a href="https://treacherous.tech/yolo-tech/">YOLO tech</a> series. If you've been following the news, then you'll be up on the latest about Israeli spyware vendor NSO Group, <a href="https://www.occrp.org/en/the-pegasus-project/" target="_blank">which licenses its Pegasus intrusion software</a> to various corrupt regimes and dictators to target human rights activists, political opponents, civil society leaders <a href="https://cdn.occrp.org/projects/project-p/?_gl=1*3exyzb*_ga*MTYzNzgzNjE4NC4xNjIwNjUzODA0*_ga_NHCZV5EYYY*MTYyNjgxNDU3Mi45LjEuMTYyNjgxNDYwNC4yOA..#/professions/journalist" target="_blank">and journalists</a>.&nbsp; This kind of thing is why <a href="https://treacherous.tech/yolo.html">YOLO devices</a> -- those gadgets you want to connect with the unwashed and the unknown -- should exist. They can be the expendable team. The tech that can take the hit without bringing everything else down.&nbsp; Here's a work station you can use to open files you get from strangers on the internet and when your done with your work, easily wipe it before using it ever again.
  </p>

  <p>
    In an <a href="https://treacherous.tech/hosting-a-secure-contact-form.html">earlier post</a>, we looked at how a journalist can create a secured, anonymous way for sources to send files and messages using Onionshare on a Raspberry Pi. Receiving files, though, is just the first thing. What happen they start landing? In may ways, if you've done this, you haven't solved a problem so much as you've invited more of them into your life. Sorry 'bout that. What you'll now want is a secure way to check your Onionshare device, initially examine the files on it, and figure out what to do with them. So, our next piece of <a href="https://treacherous.tech/yolo.html">YOLO tech</a> is the weigh station machine.&nbsp;
  </p>

  <p>
    People will send you a lot of nonsense. Someone might send you something useful. Or they might just drop some malware disguised as an interesting looking PDF file. Eiither way, you really don't want to download whatever lands in your Onionshare folder straight onto your nice reporting machine without first checking it out. All strange files are suspect. Those coming from strangers on the internet are even more suspect. So, let's create a an airlock to check these files out, open them up, read them and see what they're really made of. In this way, these files don't stay on your Onionshare Pi, and they don't reach your reporting machine. This is reportedly what happens when people use <a href="https://securedrop.org/" target="_blank">SecureDrop</a> properly: the files are moved to a <a href="https://docs.securedrop.org/en/stable/journalist.html#moving-documents-to-the-secure-viewing-station" target="_blank">mid-way laptop for opening and inspecting</a>. We're going to replicate this step on the cheap.
  </p>

  <p>
    For our own home brew limbo machine, we're going to use <a href="https://tails.boum.org/" target="_blank">Tails OS</a>. This is a secured, Linux operating system that's portable and can run on many types of computers from a USB stick. By default it's also an amnesiac, meaning, when you turn it off, anything that was done is lost, and next time you turn it on, it starts fresh. Whatever machine that's running it will also have no record of any activity. It can useful to carry a Tails USB around, because then a lot of different computers can be your computer, and when you're done, there's no trace you were on it. All its internet traffic is channeled through the Tor network as well, so your web visits stay private and you can stay more anonymous.
  </p>

  <p>
    But none of that is related to our use case this time. We just want to have an operating system that will take a bullet for us. The reason we're using it here is fairly straight-forward: It's cheap, secure, and if something goes wrong, it's easy to erase, reboot and start again, and the computer you're using it on will almost surely be fine as well. For more about Tails, <a href="https://tails.boum.org/doc/index.en.html" target="_blank">the documentation is here</a>.&nbsp;
  </p>

    <h3 id="ingredients-for-our-recipe">
      Ingredients for our recipe
    </h3>

  <ul>
    <li><strong>1 USB stick </strong>for running the Tails OS (minimum recommendation is 8gb, but for doing things with reasonably sized files, I say go large. I'm running mine on a 64gb stick)</li><li><strong>A desktop or laptop machin</strong><strong>e</strong> with a 64-bit x86-64 compatible processor. I'm running mine on an old, fairly damaged Lenovo Thinkpad E560 that work was getting ready to recycle. The point is, you don't need anything very special for this. Try looking around pawn shops or second-hand sores, you can find something for £150 or likely less that will fit the bill. It's possible someone you know has a machine in a closet they think is toast, but will work for this. We aren't using our reporting laptop because we want to separate our systems and it's likely you'll want to run both Tails and do your reporting at the same time.</li><li><strong>A second USB</strong> for storing your settings, passwords, moving files, etc.</li>
  </ul>

  <p>
    <b>Software used:</b> <a href="https://tails.boum.org/">Tails OS</a> (note, the site has broken SSL on many pages. Welcome to open source software. It does work well in the Tor Browser and nothing else), <a href="https://filezilla-project.org/" target="_blank">Filezilla</a>, <a href="https://keepassxc.org/" target="_blank">KeePassXC</a>, and <a href="https://veracrypt.fr/en/Home.html" target="_blank">Veracrypt</a>.
  </p>
<hr class="separator separator--dots" />

    <h3 id="the-recipe">
      The recipe
    </h3>

  <p>
    <b>Let's make USB stick with Tails OS on it.</b> Install Tails on your USB stick. <a href="https://tails.boum.org/doc/index.en.html" target="_blank">Go to this page</a>, scroll down to "Download, installation, and upgrade" and choose the machine you have for the download file and set up instructions. Follow those. It's pretty clear and I won't be going through them here. I did mine on a Mac. You may have something else.
  </p>

  <p>
    <strong>Try it out on your Tails USB.</strong>&nbsp;Drop it in your weigh station machine and see if everything is working. I'm assuming it's a PC of some sort, so <a href="https://tails.boum.org/doc/first_steps/start/pc/index.en.html" target="_blank">find yours here</a> to see how to make it load Tails. I went into the BIOS settings and altered the boot order so it always tries to load from the USB port first.
  </p>

  <p>
    <strong>Let's make our Tails OS persistent. </strong>Why? Because this is is a YOLO device, not a burner machine. We're going to get a few uses out of it, and likely just keep it running as it's our laptop for checking our Onionshare Pi. Persistence means that Tails will keep a little encrypted section that will maintain your settings and any other data or apps you install. Tails can walk you through setting up a persistent volume pretty easily, <a href="https://tails.boum.org/doc/first_steps/persistence/configure/index.en.html" target="_blank">but here's the the how-to if you need it</a>. Be sure to <a href="https://tails.boum.org/doc/first_steps/persistence/backup/index.en.html" target="_blank">back it up</a>!
  </p>

  <p>
    <strong>Let's add an FTP client.</strong> For whatever damned reason, Tails doesn't come with an FTP tool. Don't get me started. But we want one of these because it's easier to check the Onionshare Pi via SFTP than it will be to unmount and mount the Raspberry Pi's USB stick all the time, restarting Onionshare and so forth. So, we're going to add FileZilla to our persistent Tails volume. To do that:
  </p>

  <ul>
    <li><a href="https://tails.boum.org/doc/first_steps/welcome_screen/administration_password/index.en.html" target="_blank">Set up an administrator password</a> when starting Tails.</li><li>After Tails launches, go into the "Applications" menu in the nav bar and go to:<br>System Tools &gt;&nbsp;Synaptic Package Manager.</li><li>Use your admin password.</li><li>Search for Filezilla</li><li>Tick the box for the latest version, and in the pop-up, select "mark for installation."</li><li>Click the "apply" button, then click "apply" in the pop up window, because you mean it.&nbsp;</li><li>Let things download and then when asked, click "Install every time" or Tails won't remember to keep Filezilla if it shuts down and restarts. Then click "close" on the "changes applied" box, because for some reason that exists.</li>
  </ul>

  <p>
    <b>Configure the FTP client to reach your Onionshare Raspberry Pi.</b> So, now Filezilla exists on your Tails OS. Find it in "Applications" under "Internet" nestled between your Electrum Bitcoin wallet and Onions Circuits. Open that up. If you recall from our <a href="https://treacherous.tech/hosting-a-secure-contact-form.html">Onionshare post</a>, you had set up a way to SSH into your Onionshare device from your laptop to set it up. Those credentials will work in your SFTP client.&nbsp; You should have these saved in a KeePassXC password manager if you followed things to the letter. If not, hopefully you've got it in a SAFELY stored offline text file. Because now you need it.
  </p>

  <p>
    The Host is your Pi's IP address. Then the username is your ssh user, and the password is your ssh password. And the port will be <code>22</code>, unless you did extra credit work and futzed with that. Now navigate to your <code>/media/USB</code> directory in the Raspberry Pi (if you called it that). You should see anything that's been dropped there, including the happy little hello.txt file we made. Try downloading that into Tails and opening it to make sure things are working.
  </p>

    <h3 id="test-it-out">
      Test it out
    </h3>

  <p>
    Let's take our new set up for a test drive. You now have an Onionshare device to get files, and a Tails OS laptop to look at them. Send yourself a PDF. <a href="https://www.article19.org/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/Myanmar-Internet-Briefing-Paper-UPDATED.pdf" target="_blank">Here's one, now</a>.&nbsp; Save&nbsp;<code>Myanmar-Internet-Briefing-Paper-UPDATED.pdf</code> somewhere on your computer (not the Tails one, obvs). Open up the Tor Browser and visit your Onionshare form. Send the file along with a friendly text message. Now that you've done that, go to Filezilla in Tails and check your USB directory. You should see a new directory in there that you can download to your Tails machine and open. I saved it in Documents, which can be found under "places" in the nav bar.
  </p>

  <p>
    And that's it, we have two pieces of our YOLO tech setup, now. We haven't yet looked at the operational security of using these yet, and we have one more device to cover: The YOLO phone.
  </p>

    <h3 id="final-bits-and-pieces">
      Final bits and pieces
    </h3>

  <p>
    Some homework before starting the next post...
  </p>

  <ol>
    <li>Tails comes installed with KeePassXC. Create a database to store your FTP and SSH credentials for the Onionshare Pi. From now on, you will only access the Pi from the Tails machine. <a href="https://keepassxc.org/docs/KeePassXC_UserGuide.html" target="_blank">Learn the finer points of password management with KeePassXC here</a>.</li><li>Tails also has Veracrypt installed. This is a tool for created encrypted file storage volumes. When you decide you want to work with a file you've inspected on Tails, you're going to want to transport it (or a redacted, meta-scrubbed copy of it or a flattened export or a screenshot of it) on a USB stick to your work machine. You're work machine will never network to the Tails machine. Also, you want to secure the USB stick. <a href="https://www.veracrypt.fr/en/Home.html" target="_blank">Learn how to make an encrypted volume with Veracrypt on your USB stick here</a>. You'll also need to install Veracrypt on the device the USB is moving files to, but it has versions for Mac Windows and Linux.</li>
  </ol>

  <p>
    <b>Next post: </b>Working with files.
  </p>
<hr class="separator separator--dots" />

    <h3 id="notes">
      Notes
    </h3>

  <p>
    There are a few operating systems that run on USBs, and some that are highly secure themselves. I thought about just setting up <a href="https://www.qubes-os.org/" target="_blank">Qubes</a> and forgetting about both Tails and the Raspberry Pi. In Qubes you can create isolated environments for each. But that would require a fairly impressive machine, and these posts are focused on low-cost options. Qubes is great, but it's also not single-purpose. It's good. Great even. It's not YOLO.
  </p>

  <p>
    It's worth noting that Tails also has Onionshare pre-installed. The issue with this is that Tails software versions are often not up to date, and it's only the latest version of Onionshare that really suits our needs. Also, you don't want collection and analysis to happen on the same device. Finally, we want our secure contact webform to stay on all the time, while we might want to turn off our laptop and put it away. Your work computer is a lousy web server.
  </p>

  <p>
    Conceivably there are a few options you could use to connect to you Pi from Tails. You could wire it if you want, but the Pi already has it's ethernet port plugged into the router. You could create networks with USB ports or use USB ports to hand-move things, but SFTP is both secure enough, and keeps the wires and complications down.
  </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
